Guide to the Ireland House Oral History Collection AIA.030
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Ireland House Oral History Collection
2005-2010
AIA.030
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
4.0 linear feet in 4 record cartons
Multi-generational interviews conducted since 2005 as part of an undergraduate oral history course for the Irish Studies program at New York University, under the auspices of Glucksman Ireland House and also by doctoral students and faculty.
Glucksman Ireland House.
Custodial History Note
Interviews were conducted by students in the Irish Studies program. Materials are transferred to the Archives after access copies of interviews have been created on DVDs and transcripts typed up.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Irish Immigration Reform Movement Records AIA 016
Access Restrictions
Open for research with restrictions as noted per individual interview.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by interviewee. Dates recorded refer to date of interview.
Historical/Biographical Note
Multi-generational interviews conducted since 2005 as part of an undergraduate oral history course for the Irish Studies program at New York University, under the auspices of Glucksman Ireland House.
Scope and Contents note
The Ireland House Oral History Collection consists of multi-generational interviews conducted since 2005 as part of an undergraduate oral history course for the Irish Studies program at New York University, under the auspices of Glucksman Ireland House. Each interview has been transferred to DVD; some interviews are on multiple DVDs. The collection includes summaries of interviews (not transcripts) and supporting biographical and background information on the interviewee. Original tapes of the interviews are housed separately.
Accruals Note
Additional accruals to this collection are expected.
Benson, Sean; Burns, Edward, 1968-; King, Peter T., 1944-; Minihane, Sean; Sexton, John; Irish Americans; Irish Americans |x Social life and customs.; Oral histories (document genres); Transcripts.
- A
  - Allen, Sandie, May 2, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Historical/Biographical Note
    Sandie Allen (b. London, England, 1966) is an accomplished photographer who has documented events in Boston's Irish community for almost three decades.
- B
  - Barry, Dan, Nov 3, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Dan Barry (b. 1958) is a Pulitzer Prize-winning writer for The New York Times and has covered many topics, including the World Trade Center disaster and the damage to the Gulf Coast from Hurricane Katrina. He is the author of three books, including the autobiography Pull Me Up (2004).
  - Behan, Joe, May 4, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Joe Behan (b. Dublin, Co. Dublin, 1961) has been Head Coach of the New York University Men's Soccer team since 1996. He brought the team their first two NCAA Division III Championship appearances and was named Coach of the Year in 1999 and 2010.
  - Beirne, Hilary, Oct 29, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Content Note
    Hilary Beirne was interviewed on the 26th of October, 2009 at the Glucksman Ireland House at New York University by James Herron and Linda Dowling Almeida. The topics discussed were wide and varied, starting with his background, growing up in County Roscommon, Ireland and following through his life from college days to working in Ireland in the 1970s and ‘80s to immigrating to the United States in the late ‘80s and ending with his distinguished work with the St. Patrick’s Day Parade.
    Beirne discusses his early life, growing up with nine brothers and sisters in a large farmhouse that his father, a veterinary surgeon, purchased around the time Beirne was born. He talks about his experiences in National School, and the effects that the small learning community, corporal punishment, and religious doctrine had on his education. He went to secondary school, earning high enough marks to attend college and earn a degree in agricultural studies. He discusses his first few jobs in Ireland, where he worked on projects that redesigned the way Irish farms operate and store various crops.
    He eventually left his job and immigrated to the U.S. to become a science teacher in the Bronx. It was at this time that he became involved in the New York City St. Patrick’s Day Parade, upon which a large portion of this interview is based. Beirne discusses the finances, the history, the operations and the future of the parade in great detail. He provides an excellent behind-the-scenes view of the production of one of the largest parades in the world. Beirne also discusses, in great detail, the various other Irish fraternal clubs of which he is a member.
    As a teacher, Beirne discusses his instructing methods and how he engages the student. He also spends time discussing how he became a teacher and the reasons why. He also talks about what he thinks makes a good teacher, and the necessary traits to perform the job well.
    He then returns to a broader discussion on why Irish-American heritage is important to this country, stating, “40 million Americans trace their heritage back to Ireland…” in order to show just how important the parade is.
    Throughout the interview, Beirne takes breaks from discussing his life and the parade to talk about his family. He discusses his twin brother and the unique skills he possesses that his twin does not and vice versa. He discusses the odd relationship his siblings (2 brothers, 7 sisters) had with his parents, specifically, the love and strong bond they all had with their mother and poor relationship they had with their father. He also talks about the day he left Ireland and the effects his leaving had on his mother.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR420. The interview is 2 hours and 28 minutes long, on 3 CDs. The interview took place on October 29, 2009, and the interviewers were James Herron and Linda Dowling Almedia.
    Related Archival Materials
    Interview with Tommy Smyth. Ireland House Oral History Collection, Archives of Irish America, New York University. Interview with Treasa Goodwin Smyth. Ireland House Oral History Collection, Archives of Irish America, New York University.
    Other Finding Aids Note
    This interview has been logged at ten-minute intervals, and the Word file is available upon request at irisharchives@nyu.edu.
    Hilary Beirne (b. Boyle, Co. Roscommon, 1961) is a science teacher who emigrated to New York in 1988. He is a longtime member of the New York St. Patrick's Day Parade Committee and the nephew of the late Frank Beirne.
  - Benson, Sean, Nov 29, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    Biographical Note
    Sean Benson (b. 1960), was one of the organizers of the Irish Immigration Reform Movement. He is the former Executive Director of the Emerald Isle Immigration Center and remains a member of its board.
  - Boucher, Jack, Jan 23, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Jack Boucher (b. New York, New York, 1938), a union bartender and Vietnam veteran, is the son of immigrants from County Leitrim, and County Sligo, Ireland. Raised in New York’s Washington Heights, he was a member of the youth gang the Jesters.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PCM660. The interview took place on January 23, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Bowles, Dympna Farrell, Apr 19, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Dymphna Farrell Bowles (b. Ennistown, Co. Meath, Ireland, 1922) a long-time resident of New Rochelle, New York, moved to Belfast in 1942. She married there in 1947 and later emigrated to the United States with five young children. Her sixth child was born in New York.
  - Boylan, Jim, Feb 26, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    In the interview, Boylan focuses on growing up in 1940s/50s Harlem; the racial dynamics of Harlem and the Irish living in that setting; the impact of Puerto Ricans in his neighbourhood; how Irishness is passed on to next generation; 1950s migrants coming to stay with them; and his parents first trip back to Ireland.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 160 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place on February 26, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
    Jim Boylan (b. New York, New York, 1941), is the son of 1920s immigrants from County Monaghan,Ireland. He grew up in Harlem, New York, and spent his career working in telecommunications.
  - Branley, Mary, Aug 1, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Mary Branley (b. Sligo Town, Co. Sligo, Ireland, 1962) studied Multicultural Education in Boston, taught in an inner city school, then returned to Ireland where she is a teacher and poet.
  - Brennan, John, Oct 19, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    John Brennan (b. Co. Kerry, Ireland, 1972) worked in Henry Ford & Son Ltd in Cork from 1948-1953 when he immigrated to NY, served in the US Army, and received his BA in Economics from Fordham University. He spent most of his life working in insurance.
  - Burns, Edward Sr., Nov 14, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    In this interview, Sgt. Burns discusses a range of topics, from his family's history in New York City to his own role in the New York community. Sgt Burns spends most of the interview discussing his heritage and his family history, which is an interest of his. He describes his attempts to trace his ancestry to Ireland through his paternal family, the Burns, which leads him to County Cork. His maternal family, the Fitzgeralds, led him to County Galway. Then he describes his family's place in New York, where they lived and worked.
    Burns remembers his mother, Josephine Marie Fitzgerald, born to Eddie Fitzgerald and Anna Erika Octavia Johanson. The Fitzgeralds he has traced back to County Galway, Ireland, but his grandmother, whom the family called Grandma Svenska, was from Sweden. Burns also discusses the Burns side of the family. His great-grandfather was the first to emigrate from Ireland and he believes the family is from Cork. Neither of Sgt. Burns' grandmothers were Irish. His paternal grandmother was Mary Gale, a an immigrant, believed to be French German. Burns discusses speculation and 'Burns legend' about her emigration but he admits that very little is actually known about it. The speculation is that she was at some point in her youth orphaned and migrated to Pittsburgh. What is definite, Burns discovered, is that Mary Gale and Andrew Burns were living in the same Hell's Kitchen (a famously Irish area on Manhattan's West Side) boarding house, according to the 1900 census.
    Burns discusses his paternal grandfather, Andrew Burns, at length. He recalls Pop Burns, as he called him, fondly, often calling him quite a character. He tells stories about Pop Burns' business, hauling vinegar for Fleischmann's in New York. He talks about their summers in Rockaway Beach and stories about his Pop's swimming prowess. Burns discusses Pop growing up in Hell's Kitchen and their style of dress. He also talks about Pop Burns and his friends raising pit bulls on the roof tops and his grandfather's choice to not drink, referring to him as a teetotaler.
    Burns also fondly discusses his mother, Josephine Marie Fitzgerald, who grew up in the Yorkville section of Manhattan's Upper East Side. As a young woman she worked as a secretary at Bonwit Teller, an upscale New York City department store, now closed. Burns remarks about his mother's exceptionally small feet, that were the same size as all the sample shoes delivered to the department store. One of the perks of her job was taking home the sample pairs she liked. He observed that his mother always had the most stylish footwear in the neighborhood. Burns also discusses a story, that he could never verify, that his mother played the piano at Carnegie Hall for a school performance while attending Dominican Academy on Manhattan's Upper East Side.
    Burns speaks about his different career choices, including six years in the Army Reserves. Then he discusses his tenure with the New York Police Department (NYPD). He recalls his entry into the police academy on 20 June 1966 and being out on the street to keep the peace during riots in Harlem two weeks later on 4 July 1966. Burns spent 27 years working for the NYPD in various aspects. He remained at the 25th precinct in Harlem until 1970. Burns then became a plain clothes officer working for public morals, a division of the NYPD that deals with liquor, gambling, and prostitution violations. Burns was transferred to Glendale, Queens, for two years which he describes as the most boring part of his police career. While Burns was investigating recruits the NYPD came out with their Law Enforcement Assistance Program. Burns took advantage of the program and completed a degree in Criminal Justice at Saint John's University, resuming a college career that he quit to join the Army Reserves. During this time Burns was also studying to be a sergeant and working full time. As a sergeant with the NYPD he began working at the Office of the Deputy Commissioner, Public Information (DCPI) where Burns was the voice of the NYPD. Burns discusses how this change in his police career impacted hi life after the NYPD. Burns released official NYPD statements to the press. It was here that he became interested in the public relations business. He decided to go back to school and received his masters degree with honors from New York University in Media Ecology in 1979 or 1980. Five years later Sgt. Burns became an adjunct professor at NYU in the same program, while still working with the DCPI. Following his police career Sgt. Burns successfully opened two public relations firms. Burns also took an active role in helping his children with their careers.
    Sgt. Burn's children are a main focus of the interview. He initially lived in Astoria, Queens, with his wife and young family but moved to Valley Stream, Long Island, where he raised his family. Burns eldest child, Mary, attended the Fashion Institute of Technology and lives on Long Island. His two sons Edward and Brian, whom he calls Irish twins because they were born so close to one another in the tradition of many Catholic Irish families, are both involved in the film and television industry. Edward is a writer/director/actor for various films, including the movie that began his career, The Brothers McMullen, which won the Grand Jury Prize at the Sundance Film Festival in 1995. Burns talks with pride about his son's accomplishments. Brian is also a writer/producer for various programs including the hit HBO television show, Entourage. Sgt. Burns discussed at length his views on parenting and education.
    Sgt Burns also discusses his involvement in a group called the First Friday Club - the name alludes to a Catholic practice of attending mass for the first Friday of nine consecutive months to receive a special blessing. This group drew New York Irish American writers, politicians and intellectuals and would meet for lunch at Eamonn Doran's. Sgt. Burns describes the lunch as a meeting of friends that sometimes lasted from noon to six or seven at night. Writers like Frank and Malachy McCourt, William Kennedy, and Terry Moran were in regular attendance. Sgt. Burns describes this group as a small gathering of 10 to 12 that grew into a much larger gathering of thirty or more with the rising celebrity of members like Frank McCourt and his son Edward.
    Sergeant Edward Burns was interviewed on 14 November 2008 at the Glucksman Ireland House at New York University by Emily Mahoney and Professor Linda Dowling Almeida. Sgt. Burns' oral history interview was digitally recorded on a Marantz CD420. The interview is one hour, 57 minutes and 54 seconds long, recorded on two CDs, and has been logged in ten minute intervals.
    Sergeant Edward Burns (b. New York, New York, 1937) Sgt. Burns is a former New York City police officer with strong New York City roots and Irish ancestry. He is the father of Ed Burns, Jr., director of The Brothers McMullen.
  - Burns, Edward Jr., Oct 30, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Burns was born in Woodside, Queens, but grew up in Valley Stream, Long Island, which he affectionately calls “the burbs,” referring to the area as a suburb of New York City. He discusses his experience as a young Irish Catholic and his impressions and memories of a suburban childhood. Particularly interesting are his childhood revelations of being Irish.
    Burns describes the family history, as he knows it, of his mother and father. He details his mother’s childhood, as the daughter of Irish immigrants, growing up without a mother and a father who worked as a sandhog and who was often absent. He believes that his father’s family emigrated from Ireland during the potato famine. Burns traces the professions of his various paternal relatives, including a great-grandfather who owned a horse and carriage trucking company on the west side of Manhattan.
    Burns explains the process of making The Brothers McMullen and the various challenges that he faced in shooting the film on a low budget. He tells a few stories of the more unique things he had to do to get “the shot”, including sneaking into a graveyard.
    Burns took The Brothers McMullen to the Sundance Film Festival in 1995. Burns’ retelling of his acceptance to Sundance is particularly interesting and at the end of his story, Burns notes “Print the legend.” The Brothers McMullen won the Grand Jury Prize, which is the equivalent of the Oscar for Best Picture. Burns relates his memories of winning the actual award and all the strangeness that he felt in the moments after the announcement, including a possible embrace with “Sam Jackson”, the actor Samuel L. Jackson to the rest of us.
    Burns also discusses the roles of the Irish in entertainment and how they are portrayed in movies and television. Remarking about the Irish content and references in The Brothers McMullen, “none of this has been in a film, so I’m going to put all of it in” almost to the point of going overboard. He also discusses prominent Irish authors whose work he enjoys. Burns explains that he has attempted to adapt a couple of Irish-American novels into films, but to date none have worked.
    Burns continues to discuss the portrayal of Irish Americans on film and television. He notes that most of the Irish-American characters on film and television tend to be police officers, fire fighters or other stereotypically Irish professions. What Burns says had not been portrayed before was an Irish-American family and their everyday existence.
    Burns discusses his family’s drive for the next generation to leave the New York suburbs and return to Manhattan, which Burns has done. Burns’ father pushed Burns and his brother to attend college and to pursue the American dream of “doing better” than the previous generation. Burns juxtaposes this ambition with the fact that none of the parents of his friends in Valley Stream had gone to college. He draws the analogy of his own social climbing to the old saying “When your grandfather came here there were signs that said ‘No Irish Need Apply’ and in 1963 we put JFK in the White House.”
    Near the conclusion of the interview, Burns defines what his perception of Irish American is and what it means to him.
    Edward Burns was interviewed on October 30, 2007 at Glucksman Ireland House at New York University by Callan Stout, Linda Dowling Almeida, and Joe Ready. This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR420. The interview is 1 hour and 25 minutes long, recorded on two CDs and has been broken into tracks of ten-minute segments.
    Edward Burns, Jr. (b. Queens, New York, 1968) a writer, director, and actor who shot to fame in 1995 when his film The Brothers McMullen, about three Irish American brothers coming of age on Long Island won the Grand Jury Prize at the Sundance Film Festival. He is the son of Edward Burns, Sr.
  - Butler, Aoife E., Apr 9, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Aoife E. Butler (b. Ballinasloe, Co. Galway, 1975), a pharmaceuticals industry researcher, is active with the Irish Network U.S.A., an organization aimed at attracting young Irish professionals. She has also been a volunteer for children with disabilities.
  - Butler, Jean, Apr 21, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Jean Butler (b. Mineola, New York, 1971) is a professional dancer and choreographer. She toured with the Green Fields of America, Cherish the Ladies and the Chieftains before starring in and co-choreographing the original production of Riverdance in 1994. She has a Master's degree in Contemporary Irish Dance from the University of Limerick.
  - Byrne, Gabriel, Nov 17, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Gabriel Byrne (b. Dublin, Ireland, 1950) is an actor and producer who works in theatre and film. In 2010 he was named the Cultural Ambassador for Ireland and spearheaded "Imagine Ireland," a program that featured 400 cultural events across the United States.
- C
  - Cagney, Bridget, Nov 8, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Bridget Cagney (b. Cork, Co. Cork, 1937), is a retired program analyst for the Institute of International Education and member of “Point Thank You,” a post-9/11 support group in New York City.
  - Caine, Rosemary, Apr 29, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    Rosemary Caine (b. Ardee, Co. Louth, Ireland, 1945) is a Bunratty Castle banquet singer. She performs and directs her own theatrical productions in the United States and Ireland based on themes from Irish history.
  - Callaghan, Margaret, Aug 2, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Margaret Callaghan (b. New York, New York, 1934, d. Queens, New York, 2012), the daughter of immigrants from County Armagh, was raised in Manhattan and later resided in Queens, New York. She worked as a dental assistant and was a longtime member and leader in the Armagh Association of New York.
    Margaret Callaghan Papers (AIA 059)
  - Campbell, Colm, Nov 13, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Colm Campbell (b. 1935), is Executive Director of the New York Irish Center in Long Island City, former Director of the Irish Apostolate USA, and former Director of Youth Services for the Diocese of Down and Connor in Northern Ireland.
  - Carey, Governor Hugh, Jun 25, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview took place on June 25, 2009, and the interviewer was Peter Quinn.
    Other Finding Aid Note
    A partial transcript of this interview has been created, and the Word file is available upon request at irisharchives@nyu.edu.
    Hugh Carey (April 11, 1919-August 7, 2011) was an Irish American attorney, a seven-term United States Representative (1961-1974), and the 51st Governor of New York (1975-1982).
  - Carey, Meghan, Apr 6, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Meghan Carey (b. Southfield, Michigan, 1989) was raised in Michigan by an Irish American father and a mother of Bermudian heritage. She moved to New York to attend New York University.
  - Carr, Darrah, Apr 13, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Darrah Carr (b. Toledo, Ohio, 1974) is a dance professional who received her MFA from New York University's Tisch School of the Arts. In 2005 she founded ModERIN, a dance company that combines traditional Irish step with contemporary modern dance. She is also the North American Editor of Dance Insider.
  - Carroll, Martina, Feb 20, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Martina Carroll (b. Doolough, Geesala, Co. Mayo, c. 1920), the youngest of 11 children, emigrated to New York in the late 1940s. She married Bernard Carroll, who was the sexton of St. Patrick's Cathedral for fifty-six years, and raised three children (including Patrick Carroll and Mary Carroll French) in Stuyvesant Town on the east side of Manhattan.